Council on Foreign Relations Digital Sound Recordings, 1953-1989: Finding Aid MC104.13
Public Policy Papers
- Series 1: Digital Sound Recordings, 1953-1989; 24 boxes
  - The United States Role in the Middle East, 1957 January 14; Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Hoskins, Harold B.; 1 box (Box 733)
    American embassy in Cairo, and for American diplomatic missions in Lebanon,
    Palestine, Iraq, Iran, Saudi Arabia, and Ethiopia over the course of his career.
    From 1955 until his retirement in 1961, he served as director of the Foreign Service
    Institute.
  - Report on the Suez Problem, 1957 April 5; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-72A
  - Recent Developments in the Middle East and Eastern Europe, 1957 January 15; Menon, V. K. Krishna; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-72B
  - Neutralism in Asia, 1957 January 23; Crowe, Philip K.; McClintock, Robert; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-73A
    Speech focuses on Cambodia.
  - The Suez Crisis: Its Effect on the European Economy and Its Impact on International Oil Policies, 1957 January 28; Dorr, Goldthwaite Higginson, 1876-1977; Levy, Walter James, 1911-1997; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-73B
  - The Effect of Recent Developments on the Role of the United Nations, 1957 January 31; Bokhari, Ahmed S.; Gross, Ernest A.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-74
  - The Future of Euratom, 1957 February 13; Dean, Gordon; Kohnstamm, Max; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-75A
  - United States Policy in the Middle East, 1957 February 14; Altschul, Frank, 1887-1981; Malik, Charles; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-75B
  - A Labour View on British Foreign Policy, 1957 February 19; Healey, Denis; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-76A
  - Germany and the East, 1957 February 28; Debevoise, Eli Whitney; Kiesinger, Kurt Georg, 1904-1988.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-76B
  - Report on Germany, 1957 March 7; Conant, James B.; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-77A
  - The Problems of France Today, 1957 April 4; Dillon, C. Douglas (Clarence Douglas), 1909-2003; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-78A
    Brief unrelated snippet of audio precedes actual program by 25 seconds. Level of Dillon speech relatively low. Ends abruptly. Portions of this recording may have poor audio quality.
  - Impressions of his Trip Around the World, 1957 April 2; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986.; 1 box (Box 733)
    MC104-78B
    Tape begins with disconnected snippets of audio, possibly from earlier recording. Question and answer session levels at end of tape low but intelligible. Program ends abruptly.
  - Report on Poland, 1957 April 11; Shuster, George N.; Stone, Shepard; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-79A
  - Canada's Economic Prospects, 1957 April 16; Gordon, Walter; McKittrick, Thomas H.; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-79B
  - The Situation in Hungary, 1957 April 18; Sargeant, Howland H.; Wailes, Edward T.; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-80A
  - The Principal Probles of Anglo-American Relations, 1957 April 23; Aldrich, Winthrop W. (Winthrop Williams), 1885-1974; Douglas, Lewis W. (Lewis Williams), 1894-1974; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-80B
  - Iran: An Appreciation, 1957 April 24; Chapin, Selden; Gross, Ernest A.; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-81A
  - The Situation in Cuba, 1957 May 1; Braden, Spruille, 1894-1978; Matthews, Herbert L.; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-81B
  - Untitled, 1957 May 13; Diem, Ngo Dinh; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-82A
  - Present Realities and Prospects in Poland, 1957 May 16; Ehrlich, Ludwik, 1889-1968; Mosely, Philip E. (Philip Edward), 1905-1972; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-82B
  - Developments in the Soviet Union and Its External Relations, 1957 May 17; Bohlen, Charles E. (Charles Eustis), 1904-1974; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-83A
  - The Situation in Indonesia, 1957 May 20; Collings, L. V.; Cumming, Hugh S., Jr.; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-83B
  - Untitled, undated; Del Corral, Martin; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-84A
    Most of the session is blank.
  - Economic Development in Puerto Rico, 1957 June 17; Munoz Marin, Luis; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-84B
  - My Trip to Africa, 1957 October 3; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-85A
    Adlai Ewing Stevenson, governor of Illinois (1949-1953), Democratic candidate for President in 1952 and 1956, and United States ambassador to the United Nations (1961-1965), was born in Los Angeles, California on February 5, 1900, the son of Lewis G. Stevenson and Helen Davis Stevenson. He grew up in Bloomington, Illinois, where his ancestors had been influential in local and national politics since the nineteenth century. Jesse Fell, his maternal great-grandfather, a prominent Republican and an early Lincoln supporter, founded the Daily Pantagraph, a Bloomington newspaper. His paternal grandfather, Adlai E. Stevenson, served as Grover Cleveland's Vice President during his second term, was nominated for the office with William Jennings Bryan in 1900, and ran unsuccessfully for Illinois governor in 1908.
    Stevenson attended preparatory school at Choate and went on to Princeton University, where he served as managing editor of the Daily Princetonian and was a member of the Quadrangle Club. He graduated in 1922 and matriculated at Harvard University Law School. However, in July 1924, he returned to Bloomington to work as assistant managing editor of the Daily Pantagraph while the Illinois courts probated his grandfather's will, determining share ownership of the newspaper. While working at the newspaper, Stevenson reentered law school at Northwestern University, and in 1926, graduated and passed the Illinois State Bar examination. He obtained a position at Cutting, Moore and Sidley, an old and conservative Chicago law firm, and became a popular member of Chicago's social scene. In 1928, he married Ellen Borden, a wealthy Chicago socialite. They had three sons: Adlai E. Stevenson III (1930-); Borden Stevenson (1932-); and John Fell Stevenson (1936-). The couple divorced in 1949.
    In the early 1930s, Stevenson began his involvement in government service. In July 1933, he became special attorney and assistant to Jerome Frank, general counsel of the Agricultural Adjustment Administration (AAA) in Washington, D. C. In 1934, after the repeal of Prohibition, Stevenson joined the staff of the Federal Alcohol Control Administration (FACA) as chief attorney. A subsidiary of the AAA, the FACA regulated the activities of the alcohol industry. He returned to Chicago and the practice of law in 1935. During this time, Stevenson also became involved in civic activities, particularly as chairman of the Chicago branch of the Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies (known often as the White Committee, in honor of its founder, William Allen White). The Stevenson's purchased a seventy-acre tract of land on the Des Plaines River near Libertyville, Illinois where they built a house. Although he spent comparatively little time at Libertyville, Stevenson considered the farm home.
    In 1940, Colonel Frank Knox, newly appointed by President Franklin D. Roosevelt as Secretary of the Navy, offered Stevenson a position as his special assistant. In this capacity, Stevenson wrote speeches, represented Secretary Knox and the Navy on committees, toured the various theatres of war, and handled many administrative duties. From December 1943 to January 1944, he participated in a special mission to Sicily and Italy for the Foreign Economic Administration to report on the country's economy. After Knox's death in 1944, Stevenson returned to Chicago and attempted to purchase Knox's controlling interest in the Chicago Daily News, but another party outbid his syndicate.
    After the war, he accepted an appointment as special assistant to the Secretary of State to work with Assistant Secretary of State Archibald MacLeish on a proposed world organization. Later that year, he went to London as Deputy United States Delegate to the Preparatory Commission of the United Nations Organization, a position he held until February 1946. In 1947, Louis A. Kohn, a Chicago attorney, suggested to Stevenson that he consider running for political office. Stevenson, who had toyed with the idea of entering politics for several years, entered the Illinois gubernatorial race and defeated incumbent Dwight H. Green in a landslide. Principal among his achievements as Illinois governor were reorganizing the state police, cracking down on illegal gambling, and improving the state highways.
    Early in 1952, while Stevenson was still governor of Illinois, President Harry S. Truman proposed that he seek the Democratic nomination for president. In a fashion that was to become his trademark, Stevenson at first hesitated, arguing that he was committed to running for a second gubernatorial term. Despite his protestations, the delegates drafted him and he accepted the nomination at the Democratic National Convention in Chicago with a speech that according to contemporaries, "electrified the nation." He chose John J. Sparkman, an Alabama Senator, as his running mate. Stevenson's distinctive speaking style quickly earned him the reputation of an intellectual and endeared him to many Americans, while simultaneously alienating him from others. His Republican opponent, enormously popular World War II hero General Dwight D. Eisenhower, defeated Stevenson. Following his defeat, prior to returning to law practice, Stevenson travelled throughout Asia, the Middle East and Europe, writing about his travels for Look magazine. Although he was not sent as an official emissary of the U.S. government, Stevenson's international reputation gave him entree to many foreign officials.
    Back in the United States, Stevenson resumed his desultory practice of law. His national reputation, earned through his presidential campaign, made Stevenson a celebrity attorney who could pick and choose his clients. He accepted numerous speaking engagements and raised funds for the Democratic National Party, then suffering from an $800,000 deficit. Many Democratic leaders considered Stevenson the only natural choice for the presidential nomination in 1956 and his chances for victory seemed greater after Eisenhower's heart attack late in 1955. Although his candidacy was challenged by Tennessee Senator Estes Kefauver and New York Governor W. Averell Harriman, Stevenson campaigned more aggressively to secure the nomination, and Kefauver conceded after losing a few key primaries. To Stevenson's dismay, former president Harry S. Truman endorsed Harriman, but the blow was softened by former first lady Eleanor Roosevelt's continued support. Stevenson again won the nomination at the Democratic National Convention in Chicago. He permitted the convention delegates to choose Estes Kefauver as his running mate, despite stiff competition from John F. Kennedy. However, Stevenson's best campaign efforts could not overcome the popularity of incumbent Dwight D. Eisenhower. On November 6, 1956, Stevenson was again defeated by Eisenhower, this time by a larger margin.
    Despite his two defeats, Stevenson remained enormously popular with the American people. Early in 1957, Stevenson resumed law practice with associates W. Willard Wirtz, William McC. Blair, Jr. and Newton Minow. He also accepted an appointment on the new Democratic Advisory Council, with other prominent Democrats, including Harry S. Truman, David L. Lawrence, and John F. Kennedy. He continued to serve on the board of trustees of the Encyclopedia Brittanica and to act as their legal counsel.
    Prior to the 1960 Democratic National Convention, Stevenson announced that he was not seeking the Democratic nomination for president, but would accept another draft. Because he still hoped to be a candidate, Stevenson refused to give the nominating address for relative newcomer John F. Kennedy, a cause for future strained relations between the two politicians. Once Kennedy won the nomination, Stevenson – always an enormously popular public speaker – campaigned actively for him. Due to his two presidential nominations and previous United Nations experience, Stevenson perceived himself as an elder statesman and a natural choice for Secretary of State, an opinion shared by many.
    In December 1960, Kennedy offered Stevenson the position of United States Ambassador to the United Nations. Stevenson refused to accept or decline the ambassadorship until Kennedy named the Secretary of State, deepening the rift between them. After Kennedy appointed Dean Rusk as Secretary of State, Stevenson accepted the U.N. ambassadorship. Although he was initially insulted by the offer, once he accepted the appointment, Stevenson devoted himself wholeheartedly to his responsibilities. He served as president of the Security Council and advocated arms control and improved relations with the new nations of Africa. He established residency in an apartment at the Waldorf Astoria, and threw himself into the busy social scene of the city.
    In April 1961, Stevenson suffered the greatest humiliation of his career. After an attack against Fidel Castro's communist forces at the Bay of Pigs, Stevenson unwittingly disputed allegations that the attack was financed and supported by the Central Intelligence Agency, claiming instead that the anti-Communist forces were supported by wealthy Cuban emigres. When Stevenson learned that he had been misled by the White House, and even supplied with CIA-forged photographs, he considered resigning the ambassadorship, but was convinced not to do so. During the summer of 1961, Stevenson toured Latin America, trying to convince leaders that Castro was a threat to all of Latin America as well as to the United States. Just a year later, in October 1962, Stevenson demonstrated his seasoned statesmanship during the Cuban Missile Crisis. After the United States discovered offensive nuclear weapons in Cuba, Stevenson confronted Soviet Ambassador Valerian Zorin in an emergency meeting of the Security Council, challenging him to admit that the offensive weapons had been placed in Cuba and that he was prepared to wait "until Hell freezes over" for Zorin's answer.
    In 1964, increasingly disillusioned with his inability to participate in the formulation of policy at the United Nations, Stevenson considered running for the U. S. Senate from New York, and was also regarded as a possible running mate for President Lyndon B. Johnson. In late 1964 and 1965, Stevenson and Secretary General U Thant began to discuss opening negotiations to end the war in Vietnam, although Stevenson publicly backed Johnson's Vietnam policies. Amid much speculation that he was considering resigning his post, Stevenson addressed the Economic and Social Council in Geneva in July 1965. During a stop in London, Stevenson died suddenly on July 14, 1965. Following memorial services in Washington, D.C. and Springfield and Bloomington, Illinois, Stevenson was interred in the family plot in Evergreen Cemetery, Bloomington, Illinois.
  - The Indian Economy, 1957 November 2; Krishnamachari, T. T.; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-85B
    Several snippets of audio and dead air precede main audio.
  - Power and Purpose: Foreign Policy Since 1945, Elihu Root Lectures, 1: The Soviet Drive for Military and Political Supremacy: How Can the West Take the Political Initiative?, 1957 October 7; Finletter, Thomas K. (Thomas Knight), 1893-1980; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-86A
  - Current Political and Economic Trends in India, 1957 October 28; Masani, Minoo R.; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-86B
  - Satellites and Scientific Development, 1957 November 21; Berkner, Lloyd V.; Rabi, Isidor I.; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-87A
  - Two Estimates: Leadership and Change in the Soviet Union, 1957 December 12; Mosely, Philip E. (Philip Edward), 1905-1972; Salisbury, Harrison E. (Harrison Evans), 1908-1993; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-87B
  - The Future of NATO, 1957 November 1; Hughes, John C.; Spaak, Paul-Henri; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-88A
  - Power and Purpose: Foreign Policy Since 1945, Elihu Root Lectures, 3: From the Defensive to the Offensive: Next Steps in United States Foreign Policy, 1957 November 4; Finletter, Thomas K. (Thomas Knight), 1893-1980; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-88B
  - The Current International Situation, 1957 November 6; Bevan, Aneurin; Gross, Ernest A.; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-89A
  - Austria and Soviet Policy in Europe, 1957 November 12; Kreisky, Bruno; Siegbert, Henry; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-89B
  - The Middle Eastern Crisis, 1957 November 14; Gross, Ernest A.; Malik, Charles; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-90
  - Communism and Tito Since Stalin, 1957 November 26; MacLean, Fitzroy H.; Mosely, Philip E. (Philip Edward), 1905-1972; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-91A
  - The Arab Refugees and Middle Eastern Problems, 1957 November 26; Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995; Labouisse, Henry R., 1904-1987; 1 box (Box 734)
    MC104-91B
    Henry R. Labouisse (1904-1987) was a distinguished American diplomat and international public servant. He served as director of the United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East (UNRWA) from 1954 to 1958 and as executive director of the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF) from 1965 to 1979. He also served as a United States government official working on the formation and implementation of foreign economic policies during World War II and the 1960s. Henry Richardson Labouisse was born in New Orleans, Louisiana on February 11, 1904. He was one of two sons of Henry Richardson Labouisse and Frances Devereaux (Huger) Labouisse. He married Elizabeth Scriven Clark on June 29, 1935 and they had one daughter, Anne (Farnsworth). Elizabeth Labouisse died in 1945. Labouisse remarried on November 19, 1954, to Eve Curie, daughter of the scientists Pierre and Marie Curie. Curie was a renowned author and journalist. They met in 1951, while he was on the Economic Cooperation Administration (ECA) staff and she was a secretary with the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO). Labouisse earned his B.A. from Princeton University in 1926 and graduated from Harvard University Law School in 1929. He was admitted into the New York State bar the following year. Labouisse was an associate and member of the New York City law firm Taylor, Blanc, Capron and Marsh, and its successor firm Mitchell, Taylor, Capron & Marsh, from 1929 to 1941. When the United States entered the Second World War, Labouisse chose to serve his country by accepting a position in the State Department. He began there in 1941 and rose through a variety of positions over the next several years, most concerned with forming and implementing foreign economic policy. His first position was as assistant chief of the Division of Defense Materials in December 1941. He was promoted to chief of the division in February 1943. Later in 1943, he was made deputy director of the Office of Foreign Economic Coordination, and in January 1944 he was appointed chief of the Eastern Hemisphere Division. In March 1944, he was transferred to the Office of European Affairs, where he was special assistant to the director. Labouisse was appointed chief of the Foreign Economic Administration mission to France in November 1944 and served concurrently as minister for economic affairs at the American Embassy. He became special assistant to Under Secretary of State, William L. Clayton, in November 1945. Through his work with the undersecretary, and his previous work coordinating aid to various European reconstruction points, Labouisse played an important role in the aid efforts that culminated in the Marshall Plan. In July 1946, he returned to his role as special assistant to the director of the Office of European Affairs. Labouisse then served as the principal State Department officer working with the Economic Cooperation Administration (ECA) during the initial implementation of the Marshall Plan. He traveled to Paris in March 1948 as head of the mission to establish the ECA as the agency to administer United States economic aid to Europe. He returned to Europe in May 1948 as the head of the United States delegation to the Geneva meeting of the Economic Commission for Europe. Labouisse then served as coordinator of foreign aid and assistance in the State Department from June 1948 until October 1949, when he became director of British Commonwealth and Northern European Affairs. He held this post until September 1951. He began arguing for a tougher stance on aid in 1949, one that would force European economies to adjust to market forces. In September 1951, Labouisse was named head of the ECA's mission to France, journeying to Paris as head of the Marshall Plan mission. When the ECA was replaced by the Mutual Security Administration and the Foreign Operations Administration, Labouisse headed the Paris missions of both agencies from 1951 to June 1954. Labouisse left United States government service in 1954 to work for the United Nations. He was appointed director of the United Nations Relief and Work Agency for Palestine Refugees (UNRWA) in June 1954 at the request of United Nations Secretary-General Dag Hammarskjöld. The UNRWA was established in December 1949 to carry out relief and works projects in cooperation with local governments. When Labouisse assumed his directorship, the UNRWA was responsible for the care of 887,000 Arab refugees who had fled Palestine in 1948. Labouisse oversaw the improvement of the standard of living in the refugee camps, raised the standards of health, education, and vocational training, and established a grant program that allowed refugees to make a down payment on a farm or shop. He left the UNRWA in 1958. Labouisse was appointed as a consultant to the International Bank of Reconstruction and Development in May 1959. He headed a survey mission to Venezuela in September 1959 to assist in the formulation of a program of economic development. He was recalled from that mission by Hammarskjöld to serve as special advisor to the secretary-general during the Congo crisis in 1960. In December 1960, Labouisse was appointed as the International Bank's special representative for Africa and also headed a mission to Uganda to study economic problems. He returned to United States government service in January 1961, when he was appointed Director of the International Cooperation Administration (ICA) by President John F. Kennedy, which was created to coordinate nonmilitary foreign aid programs. Labouisse had been considered for the post by President Dwight D. Eisenhower in February 1959, but his appointment was rejected by Republican national chairman Meade Alcorn on the grounds that Labouisse had registered as a Democrat several years earlier. In May 1961, President Kennedy began to work with Congress to reorganize the foreign aid programs into a single agency. The ICA was eliminated during the reorganization, and Labouisse was named United States Ambassador to Greece. He held that post from 1962 to 1965. Labouisse was appointed the second Executive Director of the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF) in June 1965, following the death of the first director, Maurice Pate. During his directorship, Labouisse oversaw the emergency relief efforts for several major conflicts and naturals disasters, and fought to alleviate poor conditions in developing countries. UNICEF provided relief to both sides in the Nigerian civil war in 1968 and to Cambodia in 1979, after the country was invaded by Vietnam. Labouisse retired from his position with UNICEF in December 1979, although he continued to work as a consultant on the Cambodia and Thailand operations for most of 1980. After his retirement, Labouisse continued to be active in various organizations, including serving as Chairman of the Board of the American Farm School in Thessaloniki Greece from 1980 to 1985 and as trustee of the school from 1965 to 1985. Labouisse died on March 25, 1987.